<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<articles>
  <article type="press-release">
    <articleMeta>
      <ogURL>http://www.hrworks-inc.com/who-we-are/press-releases3/8-press-releases/429-hr-works-inc-named-to-the-best-companies-to-work-for-in-new-york-list-for-2013</ogURL>
      <redirrectURL>who-we-are/press-releases3/8-press-releases/429-hr-works-inc-named-to-the-best-companies-to-work-for-in-new-york-list-for-2013</redirrectURL>
      <publishedDate>2013-05-01 08:00:00 -0400</publishedDate>
    </articleMeta>
    <title>HR Works, Inc. named to the "Best Companies to Work for in New York" list for 2013</title>
    <body>
<![CDATA[<p>
  For more information, contact Candace Walters at 585-381-8340
  ext. 111
</p>
<p>
  HR Works, Inc. was recently named for the third consecutive year
  as a Best Companies to Work for in New York. HR Works, Inc. is
  proud to be among the top 30 companies in its category of
  small/medium with 15 to 249 employees. In total, 50 companies
  were identified for demonstrating that happy employees make for
  good business and drive the Empire state’s economy.<br>
  <br>
  The sixth annual Best Companies program is the result of a
  partnership between the New York State Society for Human Resource
  Management, Best Companies Group, Journal Multimedia Corporation
  and The Business Council of New York. The 2013 program is
  sponsored by Capital District Physicians’ Health Plan and Jackson
  Lewis, LLP.<br>
  <br>
  HR Works, Inc. was recognized and honored at the Best Companies
  to Work for in New York awards dinner on Tuesday, April 30, 2013,
  at the Albany Marriott.
</p>
<p>
  For more information on the Best Companies to Work for in New
  York awards program, visit <a href=
  "http://www.bestcompaniesNY.com">www.bestcompaniesNY.com</a>.<br>
</p>
<p>
  HR Works, Inc., located at 246 Willow Brook Office Park in
  Fairport (Rochester), New York, is a human resource management
  outsourcing and consulting firm serving more than 700 clients. HR
  Works provides benefits administration outsourcing; full-time,
  part-time and interim on-site HR managers; HR audits; legally
  reviewed employee handbooks and supervisor manuals; affirmative
  action programs; compensation programs; training of managers and
  HR professionals; and HRIS and self-service technology.
</p>]]>
    </body>
  </article>
  <article type="industry-update">
    <articleMeta>
      <ogURL>http://www.hrworks-inc.com/topics-in-hr/industry-updates/10-eeoaffirmative-action-/308-ask-the-experts-collecting-and-tracking-disposition-data</ogURL>
      <redirrectURL>topics-in-hr/industry-updates/10-eeoaffirmative-action-/308-ask-the-experts-collecting-and-tracking-disposition-data</redirrectURL>
      <publishedDate>2016-01-1 08:00:00 -0400</publishedDate>
      <relatedSolution>11</relatedSolution>
    </articleMeta>
    <title>Ask the Experts: Collecting and Tracking Disposition Data</title>
    <body>
<![CDATA[<p>
  <strong><em>Question:</em></strong> I have a hard time getting
  managers to tell me the reason why they didn’t choose to hire or
  interview a particular applicant. Is it necessary to include this
  information in my applicant flow log?
</p>
<p>
  <strong><em>Answer:</em></strong> Collecting and tracking
  disposition data on applicants is a challenge for many
  organizations. While it may seem like an administrative burden
  now, it is even more so when trying to recreate the data months
  or years from now when you’re trying to explain your selection
  decisions to the government.
</p>
<p>
  <em>What is disposition data?</em>
</p>
<p>
  When we talk about disposition data, we’re referring to the
  information describing each applicant’s outcome in the selection
  process. There are two key pieces of disposition data: 1) how far
  an applicant progressed through the selection process (“fallout
  stage”), and 2) why the applicant didn’t progress further
  (“reason”).
</p>
<p>
  Examples of fallout stages include: Application Materials Not
  Reviewed, Application Materials Reviewed, Phone Screened,
  Interviewed, Tested, Offered Position, and Hired. For each
  applicant you should track the last stage reached in your
  applicant log. If your organization doesn’t always follow the
  same order in the selection process, then you should document the
  stages and their order for each position.
</p>
<p>
  Examples of reasons include: Position No Longer Available, Did
  Not Meet Basic Qualifications, Desired Salary/Work
  Location/Schedule Inconsistent with Position, Applicant Withdrew,
  More Qualified Candidate Chosen, and Offer Declined. It’s
  important to have a set of reason codes that are meaningful for
  your organization or you’ll find that they aren’t being used
  consistently.
</p>
<p>
  For both cases, it is best to have a standard set of disposition
  choices rather than free entry. We have seen free entry include
  comments like, “Special Olympics” in the applicant log. This
  could be interpreted multiple ways: Is it a former employer? Is
  the applicant a philanthropic volunteer? Is it a thinly veiled
  attempt at documenting a disability that may or may not actually
  prevent the applicant from performing the job? Even the person
  who wrote it may be unable to remember the meaning if asked
  months or years later.
</p>
<p>
  <em>Why track disposition data?</em>
</p>
<p>
  Applicant disposition data is important for several reasons. In
  the short-term, it influences who is included in your analyses
  when you review your selection decisions for race- or
  gender-based disparities (adverse impact analyses). Under the
  OFCCP’s Internet Applicant Definition, people can be excluded
  from the applicant analysis for reasons such as not meeting the
  basic qualifications and withdrawing either actively or
  passively. (<a href=
  "http://www.dol.gov/ofccp/regs/compliance/faqs/iappfaqs.htm#Q1WC">Click
  here</a> for more information.) Without this information, you
  will include people in the analysis who shouldn’t be included and
  potentially make it appear that a disparity exists where one does
  not.
</p>
<p>
  By using a standardized set of disposition reasons, you may
  prevent a recruiter or hiring manager from excluding an applicant
  for an unlawful reason. If the person making the decision is
  unable to choose an appropriate reason from your list, he or she
  should review the reason with HR or another manager to make sure
  it’s an acceptable reason.
</p>
<p>
  Documenting acceptable reasons for not choosing an applicant will
  also help you defend the organization against charges of
  discrimination. Being able to explain why a selection decision
  was made can prevent further questioning and unnecessary legal
  expense.
</p>
<p>
  Similarly, when OFCCP auditors find statistically significant
  selection disparities (adverse impact) or receive a complaint
  they usually ask for more information –fallout stage, reason, or
  both. If you don’t have the data, the agency will either request
  the raw documents to try to recreate it or assume the worst.
</p>
<p>
  <em>How should disposition data be collected?</em>
</p>
<p>
  The collection of disposition data is going to depend a lot on
  your selection process and who is involved.
</p>
<ol>
  <li>Make sure everyone involved in the process understands their
  role and the risk involved in not properly tracking applicant
  data.
  </li>
  <li>Designate at least one person who will be accountable for
  auditing the data periodically to ensure it is complete.
  </li>
</ol>
<p>
  Memories fade over time, so the data should be collected as close
  to the time of the decision as possible. You may find it helpful
  to give managers a form that lists the candidates and disposition
  choices so they can submit the disposition data to the person
  responsible for applicant tracking when the selection process is
  complete.
</p>
<p>
  HR Works, Inc. offers sample tools to assist you in this process,
  including disposition codes, a job tracking form, and guidance on
  the internet applicant definition. For more information,
  contact your affirmative action project manager.
</p>]]>
    </body>
  </article>
  <article type="article" author="candace-walters" inRBJ="true">
    <articleMeta>
      <ogURL>http://www.hrworks-inc.com/our-solutions/benefits-administration-outsourcing/benefits-articles/359-a-new-approach-to-an-old-benefits-question</ogURL>
      <redirrectURL>our-solutions/benefits-administration-outsourcing/benefits-articles/359-a-new-approach-to-an-old-benefits-question</redirrectURL>
      <publishedDate>2011-09-02 08:00:00 -0400</publishedDate>
      <relatedSolution>12</relatedSolution>
    </articleMeta>
    <title>A new approach to an old benefits question</title>
    <body>
<![CDATA[<p>
  As recently as five years ago, one challenge employers faced
  around the topic of benefits involved answering a simple
  question:
</p>
<p>
  “Do my employees fully appreciate the true cost of the pension
  plans, health insurance and other benefits provided to them?”
</p>
<p>
  The answer, of course, directly affected workforce moral, an
  organization’s ability to retain the best talent and its chance
  of maintaining a competitive edge.
</p>
<p>
  Today, that old question does not go far enough. Why? For one,
  the outlook for benefits such as health care and retirement is
  volatile at best. Secondly (and just as important) the role of
  the employee has dramatically changed. Employees no longer are
  passive recipients of benefits _ they’ve become benefit
  consumers. As such they are required to make important long-term
  decisions about 401(k) investing as well as navigate complex
  health insurance options.
</p>
<p>
  So perhaps the better question is: “how benefit literate are my
  employees?”
</p>
<p>
  The answer might be the difference between a workforce that’s
  distracted by confusion and angst and one that is galvanized,
  energized and informed.
</p>
<h3>
  Confusion is the Norm
</h3>
<p>
  The Institute of Medicine’s report “Health Literacy: A
  Prescription to End Confusion,” estimates that close to half of
  the population has difficulty understanding and using health
  information.&nbsp;&nbsp; There are similar stats on employees’
  limited understanding of retirement planning and 401(k)
  investing.&nbsp;&nbsp; And yet the decisions employees are forced
  to make every day impact their long term health and
  retirement.&nbsp;
</p>
<p>
  Telling employees that information about these complex topics is
  “on the website” no longer is acceptable, according to Michael
  Merriman, Managing Director of the Rochester-based Waterford
  Group, which provides retirement planning and asset management
  for businesses.&nbsp; Today’s more savvy employers are pushing
  benefit education by mandating workers to attend 401(k) meetings,
  for example. These employers are prepared to pay for the time
  employees spend meeting with enrollment advisors. The objective,
  Merriman said, is to develop a workforce that understands the
  options and is prepared to deal with change. Conveying benefits
  accurately is equally essential for showing evidence of
  compliance.
</p>
<p>
  There are many options today for employers to communicate
  effectively. Because people respond differently to how
  information is delivered, employers should consider using a
  variety of venues.
</p>
<p>
  Here are some suggestions:&nbsp;&nbsp;
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <strong>Group meetings</strong> and one-on-one meetings with HR
    representatives continue to be one preferred approach,
    particularly during open enrollment.&nbsp;
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Digital tools.</strong> Reinforce face-to-face meetings
    with podcasts, web-based videos and online chats. The explosive
    growth of social networking sites such as Facebook and Twitter
    have made it easier to communicate and have opened up a number
    of new ways employers can communicate with their employees.
    HRIS and intranet sites can be used to help employees break
    down potentially confusing and overwhelming amounts of benefit
    information.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Benefits-at-a-glance statements.</strong> These
    single-page overviews describe a company’s benefit offerings,
    details about eligibility, and cost to the employee.&nbsp;
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Employee handbooks.</strong> A comprehensive handbook
    enables employers to comply with federal and state statutes,
    including the New York State law requiring written
    communication of working hours and certain benefit programs. A
    handbook tailored to the employer also can serve as a long-term
    resource for communicating company policies, benefits and other
    important information to new and current employees.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Personalized employee benefit statements.</strong>
    These important communication tools are now available to
    employees year round through on-line HR technology.&nbsp; Each
    employee receives a dollars-and-cents breakdown of all the
    benefits the employer provides, in a manner that helps an
    employee feel informed and valued. Often, until an employee
    sees these described in detail, precisely as they apply to him
    or her, he or she underestimates how much the company is
    contributing toward his or her well-being.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Employee newsletters.</strong> Regular communication,
    presented in an upbeat and informational format, is especially
    effective for conveying news, providing a refresher and
    strengthening the bond between employee and employer. If sent
    to the employee’s home, his or her spouse and family members
    also feel included in the company “family.”
  </li>
</ul>
<p>
  It’s important to remember that all written material should be
  easy to read. The U.S. Department of Health and Human Services
  also suggests involving staff—including persons with limited
  health literacy—in the design and testing of benefits
  communications.
</p>
<h3>
  A Reality Check
</h3>
<p>
  Corporate America spends billions of dollars on employee benefits
  each year. Taken together, perks such as paid time off, medical
  and dental plans, disability and life insurance, flexible
  spending accounts, social security and 401(k) plans can easily
  add more than 30 -40&nbsp; percent to an employee’s annual cash
  compensation. Today, perhaps more than ever, it’s important for
  both employers and employees not only to recognize but to
  understand the value of this “hidden paycheck."&nbsp;
</p>]]>
    </body>
  </article>
</articles>
